[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Twenty-three]
[第二十三集]
Three working groups are struggling to operate.
三个打工组惨淡经营
No customers in the canteen.
食堂没有顾客
[Chen Yannian, eldest son of Chen Duxiu]
洗衣组也招揽不到客人
Only one making profits is the filming group, but barely.
冒前只有放电影勉强不亏本
We won't be able to last if it keeps up like this.
长此以往 势必难以为继
Not to mention now with this mess.
现在出了这挡子事
It overturned the public opinion that originally supported us.
颠覆了原本支持我们的社会舆论
Comrades, we can't just sit and wait for the end to come.
同志们手 我们不能坐以待毙
We must find out whoever is behind this.
必须挖出这个幕后黑手
I disagree with you.
我不同意你的看法
I think this article is not a bad thing.
我觉得这篇文章它不是个坏事
Yes, there is someone crticizing us.
你们想想 有人攻击我们
But, that is also free advertising for us.
实际上是在给我们做免费的广告
We probably should thank him.
应该感谢他才是
I agree.
我也这么想的
This Liao Zhi guy.
我觉得这个聊之
He is promoting us right now.
其实是在帮我们宣传
Think about it.
你们想啊
Are we not pursuing the freedom that we wanted now?
难道我们不是在追求向往的自由
If we are,
如果是
then what do we have to fear?
那我们有什么可害怕的
I disagree.
我不同意
I don't agree either.
我也不同意
He is clearly badmouthing us.
分明就是在低毁我们
Well, this article is...
他是这个里面
It is a bit too aggressive and biased.
说得有一点点偏激
Yannian!
延年
What's wrong?
怎么了
I met some strangers at the door just now.
我刚才在门口碰到几个陌生人
They asked me about the work-study mutual aid society.
他们向我打听工读互助社
I asked who they were looking for.
我问他们找谁
They are looking for Yi Qunxian.
他们说找易群先
I noticed there was a policeman.
我看有警察
I said I didn't know.
我就推说我不知道
But they'll know it's here soon.
我估计他们很快就找到这儿来了
So I locked up the front yard door.
所以我把前院的门给插上了
Damn.
完了完了
My dad must sent them to catch me.
是我爸派人来抓我来了
I- I don't want to go back.
那个 我我不想跟他回去
Please help me.
你们帮帮我吧
We are in the capital, the best city.
京城 乃首善之地
They can't take you against your will.
他们还敢抢人吗
Who do they think we are?
当我们吃素的
Don't be afraid, Comrade Qunxian.
群先同志 你别怕
We will protect you.
我们保护你
You and He Mengxiong.
这样 你跟何孟雄
Take her, jump out of the window in laundry room.
带着她从洗衣房的窗户跳出去
Go to the French Language Institute.
去法文进修馆
Other girls go back to the dormitory, cover them.
其他的女生回宿舍打掩护
All men, following me to open the door.
男同志跟着我去开门
Ok.
好行
Go.
走
Open the door! Open the door!
开门  开门
Open the door!
开门
Coming!
来了
What do you want?
干什么呀
We are entrusted by Congressman Yi kuilong.
我们受国会议员易夔龙的委托
Looking for his daughter, Miss Yi Qunxian.
前来寻找他的女儿易群先小姐
Then why come to us?
那 为什么到我们这儿来找
We received a report.
我们接到举报
Miss Yi was deceived into joining the work-study mutual aid society.
易小姐受骗 参加了工读互助社
She lives here.
就住在这里
There is no such person.
没这人啊
We don't know her.
我们不认识她呀
That's right.
对呀
You guys got it wrong.
你们 不对呀
We are all non-local students.
我们这儿都是外地来的学生
Didn't see her.
没有
Where is the girls' dormitory?
女生宿舍在哪儿
Do you have a search warrant?
有搜查证吗
This is not a search.
这不是搜查
This is a routine inspection.
这是例行检查
Please don't interfere with our official duties.
请不要妨碍我们执行公务
Let's move.
走
What are you doing? This is girls' dormitory!
干吗呢 女生宿舍
Stop!
站住
Where are you going?
千什么去
Put away the water.
倒水
Is this legal?
犯法吗
Everyone, stand up.
全部起立
Put your hands down.
拿出来
Sir, no sign of her in the boys' dormitory.
报告警长 男生宿舍没有
Report to the police station immediately when you find Yi Qunxian.
发现易群先 立刻向警署汇报
You will be punished if you hide her.
胆敢私 严惩不贷
Let's go.
走
Xiusong, Qiaonian.
秀松乔年
See the police off.
送送警察先生
Okay!
好
How was it?
怎么样 怎么样
Was I doing okay?
我演得还行吗
Great job.
特别棒
You're the best.
就你最聪明了
Keep doors and windows closed!
关门关窗
Thieves are not welcome!
防偷防盗
Wontons!
馄饨
Freshly made!
出锅
Keep doors and windows closed!
关门关窗
Thieves are not welcome!
防偷防盗
Wontons!
馄饨
Freshly made!
出锅
Keep doors and windows closed!
关门关窗
Comrade Yi Qunxian.
易群先同志
If you don't mind.
你要是不嫌弃
Of course I don't mind.
不嫌弃
Push!
起
Go!
走
Push harder!
使把劲
Slowly, slowly.
慢点慢点
You know someone called "Cairen"?
见没见过踩人
No idea.
没见过 没见过
All right, thanks.
好 谢谢
Excuse me, mind me asking something?
真不好意思麻烦问一下
Do you know a man called "Cairen"?
你们认识一个叫踩人的吗
Excuse me, do you know "Cairen"?
请问您认识踩人吗
Never heard of that.
没听说过
I told you that Peking University's law department is too big.
我都说了 北大法科这么大
Finding someone is like looking for a needle in a haystack.
找个人就像大海捞针一样
Are you sure that person is from Peking University?
你们确定那个人是北大的吗
Yes.
是
He interviewed me twice in private.
他私底下还采访过我两次呢
But as soon as I mentioned introducing you guys to him.
但是我一跟他提见你们
He wouldn't give me a straight answer.
他就支支吾吾的
He must be hiding something.
肯定有什么隐情
That's the guy!
就这个人
Him?
这个人
Are you sure?
你确定吗
I'm sure.
我确定
This can't be good.
那可坏事了
Wait, you know him?
不 你认识他
Not only know him.
我何止是认识
This man's name is Zhang Fengzai.
这个人叫张丰载
I dealt with him when I was in Japan.
我在日本的时候就跟他打过交道
His teacher Lin Shu is a traditionalist.
复古派林野的学生
He's a disciple of Huang Kan.
黄侃的弟子
A typical royalist.
典型的保皇派
Who cares about whose student he is?
管他谁的学生呢
[He Mengxiong, Visiting student at Peking University]
我去抓他来问问不就知道了
You are gonna just go like this?
你这么直接去抓人家
What if he denies it all?
人家到时候咬死不承认怎么力
We won't know if we don't act now.
你不问你怎么知道
Wait a second, we have few problems now.
不是现在有几个问题啊
First, we have no direct evidence
第一口 咱们没有直接的证据
to prove that he wrote the article.
能证明那文章就是他写的
Second, the argument between the new culture and the traditionalists
第二新文化跟复古派的斗争
is heating up every second.
现在已处于自热化的阶段
We can't risk involving Mr. Shouchang and Mr. Shizhi again.
别再牵连到守常先生跟适之先生
Also there is Chen Duxiu.
还有陈独秀
I think there is a bigger picture behind this.
我觉得这背后有一大局
Yannian makes sense.
延年说得有道理
He is coming out.
出来了
Hide! Hide!
快藏起来 藏起来
Hurry up!
快快快
It's too late.
来不及了
Play it by ear.
见机行事吧啊
Time to improvise.
见机行事
Yannian
延年
You- you are Tiren?
那谁踢人
Ah, wait it's Jiren.
啊叫挤人
Oh no, it's Cairen.
踩人踩人
Who are you?
你谁啊
Huh?
这
You forgot about us already?
把我们给忘了
You just did the interview few days ago.
前几天还采访来着
Isn't this Miss Yi?
这不是易小姐吗
Long time no see.
好久不见
I remember now, Mr. Garlic Clove.
我想起来了 蒜瓣先生
What is it, you want to talk to me?
怎么着 找我有事
Yes.
有事
Now answer me.
说说吧
Did you write this article?
这篇文章是不是你写的
What newspaper?
什么报纸
It was not me who wrote it
不是我写的
You didn't write it?
不是你写的
If it's not you, then who did?
不是你写的谁写的
Since the establishment of our mutual aid society,
我们互助社成立以来
the only interview we accepted was with you
就接受过你一个记者的采访
and you interviewed her again off the books.
而你私下里还约易同学
Twice secretly.
出去采访过两次
In this artice, all our members' family background was written about
这上面把我们互助社成员的
with details.
家庭背景写得是有鼻子有眼的
But everything else was total nonsense.
满嘴的胡说八道
You claimed you didn't write it, then tell me who did?
不是你写的那是谁写的
I am warning you, stop bullshiting.
告诉你别血口喷人啊
You take a good look at it.
来你看
Signature for this article is Liao Zhi, clearly.
这个署名明明是聊之
This won't work.
这样不行
What's my name?
我叫什么啊
My name is Cairen.
我叫踩人
This has nothing to do with me.
跟我有什么关系
It's the wrong person.
找错人了
You can't go.
你不能走
What, you wanna fight now?
千什么 想动手是吧
I won't do it.
我不动手
You need to come with me and tell my friends what happened.
你跟我回去 跟他们讲清楚
Why should I?
我跟你说得着吗
You can't go.
你不能走
What are you doing?
千什么
This is Peking University.
干什么
You are gonna get in trouble. Let go.
别伤着你自己 起来
Wait, come with me.
你回来你跟我回去
You!
叫你
What are you doing?
你们在千什么
So you wanna fight?
真动手是不是
Wait, where are you going.
你去干吗
You come back with me and make it clear.
你跟我回去说清楚
I have nothing to tell.
我跟你说什么说
I am gonna call for help.
我喊人了
He Mengxiong!
何孟雄
What are you doing now?
你在干什么呀
Criticizing me in the mutual aid society is not enough,
你们在互助社批斗我不成
now you harass Mr. Zhang as well?
现在来骚扰人家张先生
What proof do you have?
你有什么证据
No.
不是
What do you mean, Liu Mei?
柳眉 你什么意思
If it weren't for your fault,
要不是你闯的祸
why are we going through all this trouble?
我们费这么大劲干吗呀
What do you mean, I got into trouble first?
什么叫我闯的祸 易群先
About advertising,
当时登广告
didn't I ask everyone's opinion?
我是不是问了所有人的意见
Everyone agreed.
大家都同意了
You didn't object either.
你也没反对啊
So I invited reporter Zhang.
后来我把人家张记者请过来了
You were all been interviewed.
你们也都接受采访了
How come when something went wrong,
为什么现在出了错
It's my fault?
就是我一个人的事
I am not responsible.
我不认账
Mr. Zhang, you have no idea.
张先生 您不知道
When the newspaper came out,
当时那报纸一出啊
they turned into insane dogs.
互助社出现了一群狗
A pack of crazy dogs.
一群狂的狗
They barked at me, threw shit on me.
他们往我身上泼屎盆子
No matter how much I suffer and complain,
我再难受 再抱怨
no one would listen to me.
也没有人听我讲
I'm telling you now.
我告诉你们
I am done with this mutual aid club.
这个互助社我柳眉不待也罢
Liu Mei, you are siding with an outsider now.
柳眉 你这是胳膊肘子往外拐
If this is your attitude,
你要是今天这个态度
our mutual aid society will expel you today.
我们互助社今天就开除你
Whatever!
开除就开除
I don't care anymore.
我还不稀罕了呢
Yi Qunxian, let me tell you.
易群先 我告诉你
Don't take yourself too seriously cause your father is a congressman.
你别以为你爸是国会议员
How about that?
就怎么着
I never like you!
我早就看不惯你了
Are you crazy, Liu Mei?
疯了吧你柳眉
You really are like a rat shit.
你真是一颗老鼠屎
A rat shit that ruins a whole pot of good porridge!
坏了我们一锅粥
You call me a rat shit?
谁是老鼠屎
What about you?
我还说你呢
Your escape from marriage failed.
你逃婚不成你回家呀
Better go home before you lose the chance to marry forever!
回家你也嫁不出去
Take a good look at yourself!
媽她那副嘴脸
So what if I can't get married?
我嫁不出去 怎么着
Comrades!
各位同志
Don't argue over me.
千万别因为我伤了和气
To be honest, I do care
说实话 我是真心实意地关心
about this mutual aid society.
爱护咱们的互助社
I- I especially hope that our mutual aid society
我我特别希望咱们互助社
is like a seed,
能像一根小草
after being moistened by rain and bathed by sunshine,
经过雨水的滋润 阳光的沐浴
slowly growing into a towering tree.
慢慢地长成一棵参天大树
I especially hope that our mutual aid society
我特别希望咱们互助社
will be able to flourish.
能够欣欣向荣
So how could I possibly write this-
所以我怎么可能写这种
this kind of lousy article.
这种下三烂的文章
No need to explain to them, Mr. Zhang.
张先生 你别跟他们解释了
The people in their mutual aid society are single minded.
他们互助社的人就是一根筋
They are stubborn.
认死理
They won't listen to people.
根本听不进去人话
I'm telling you it's dark.
我跟你说黑啊
Really dark stuff in there.
实在是黑啊
I could spend three days and three nights talking about it
我三天三夜
and even that wouldn't be enough.
都跟你倒不完这个苦水
Let's walk,
走走走这样
we can find a cafe or a teahouse or something.
你找个咖啡厅或者茶馆什么的
I will tell you everything.
我跟你好好讲一讲
I want to peel off their disguise layer by layer.
我要一层一层剥下他们的画皮
Let's go.
走
You traitor!
你个吃里爬外的叛徒
I am gonna bite you to death today!
我今天咬死你
Qunxian!
群先
Come back here!
你给我回来
Liu Mei!
柳眉
I am gonna bite you to death today!
今天我就要死你
Come back!
你给我回来
Liu Mei, you're getting out of line.
柳眉 你越来越过分了啊
So this is Liu Mei playing it by ear?
这是柳眉的见机行事吗
Well played.
可以
She really pissed me off.
不气死我了
If he hadn't just stopped me,
要刚刚不是他拦着
I would've biten her already.
我都要咬她了
That was convincible enough, right?
我们俩没穿帮吧
No, no.
没有没有没有
Wonderful work.
特别棒
But Liu Mei is going alone now.
但是柳眉现在就她一个人去
I am worried that Cairen might set up a trap again.
这踩人别再使什么坏啊
You know him? Chen Yannian?
你知道这个陈延年吧
He's Chen Duxiu's eldest son.
就是陈独秀的大儿子
He tricked me into the club using sweet words.
他是花言巧语把我骗编到社里边的
If we don't take him and his father down
如果不把他和他父亲
and expose their behaviors to the world,
他们俩的行为暴露给世人
I, Liu Mei, will die with my eyes wide open.
我柳眉死都不甘心
In that case,
既然这样的话
I can help you.
我可以帮你
Really?
真的假的
Don't underestimate me.
你还真别小看我
I will tell you what's going on here.
我实话告诉你
We have been planning something big.
我们这边一直在酿一个大计划
Get close.
来
My second uncle has submitted to Congress
我二叔已经向国会提交了
a motion to impeach Cai Yuanpei, President of Peking University.
关于弹劾北大校长蔡元培的提案
Who is your second uncle?
你二叔是谁啊
His name is Zhang Changli.
他叫张长礼
Congressman.
国会议员
That's the same as Yi Qunxian's father.
那是跟易群先的爸爸是一样的
Isn't it?
是吧
Exactly.
没错
And we are working with Yi Kuilong too.
而且这次提案
The proposal is co-signed
就是我们联合易蔓龙
by the group of us.
起提交的
This time, we must take Chen Duxiu and his gang,
我们这次一定要将陈独秀这帮人
tear up the altar,
拉下神坛
and pull Chen Duxiu and the rest off the altar.
把陈独秀他们拉下神坛
One proposal won't be enough, dont you think?
光一个议案不行吧
Submitting it to the Congress
向国会提交议案
is only our first step.
只是我们的第一步
As for the second step,
我们这第二步
we also contacted a number of
还联系了多家
domestic and foreign media reporters.
国内和国外的媒体记者
Look, they are all with us.
你看 这些都是和我们
A list of journalists.
作过的记者名单
Enough from me,
不是另 别光我说呀
It's your turn to give me some information.
也该你给我爆点料了吧
Let's do it.
来吧
Shen.
老沈
These seven articles have similar themes,
这七篇稿子主题相似
written neatly.
写得还算工整
Take a look,
你看看放在
is it suitable for your column?
你的这个栏目底下合适否
Okay.
好
Hurry up and read them through.
抓紧审啊
This Chen Zhongfu...
这个陈仲甫
Didn't we say it clearly that day?
那天说得不是很明确吗
He's in charge of New Youth.
他来负责 《新青年》
But now he is never here.
天到晚见不着他的人影
So many articles!
这这么多的文章
How can two people finish reading them all?
两个人怎么看得完昵
[Gao Yihan, Professor at Peking University]
仲现在是忙得不可开交
Tons of responsibilities
千头万绪全都集中在
on his shoulder alone.
他一个人的身上
Just heard that "The Renaissance" office was being attacked
这不听说《新潮》 那边
and besieged by people.
被人围攻了
He hurried to relieve it.
他赶去解围
You two have worked hard.
二位辛苦了
Here we come.
我们来喽
We are here.
我们来楼
Drop off the manuscript again.
又送稿子来了
I'm exhausted, you guys.
真想把我累死啊你们
We didn't just come for the manuscript,
我们不光是送子来了
we came to help as well.
还是帮忙来了
Have you finished proofreading?
都校对完了吗
All done.
校对完了
Good.
好
Brother Deqian.
德潜兄
Your help arrived just in time.
你们这叫雪中送炭
Please.
有劳了
Thank you!
有劳了啊
Well, now we have food for the mind
这个 精神食粮要有
and also food for the stomach.
物质食粮也要有
[Liu Bannong, Professor at Peking University]
所以我们俩赶紧
Got you some hot food.
弄点热乎的给送过来了
How many manuscripts have you received?
收到多少稿子了
Not counted yet.
这个没统计过
Shouchang, Zhongfu, Lu Xun.
守常 仲甫鲁迅
They each wrote several articles.
都是一个人写了好几篇
Plus the others.
再加上其他的那些
In Anhui dialect, this is called a silt.
用我们安徽话讲 淤了吧
What do you mean by silt?
什么叫淤了吧
There are too many to put into use.
太多了用不了了
It's blocked up.
堵塞了
I see you're all from Anhui.
我发现你们安徽人
What's going on here?
这都是怎么了
Duan Qirui from the Anfu Department.
安福系的段祺瑞
Xu Shuzheng from Anhui.
徐树是安徽的
Chen Duxiu and Hu Shi at Peking University.
北大这边陈独秀 胡适
You, Gao Yihan, are from Anhui.
你高一涵是安徽的
And the director of the metropolitan police department
还有那个京师警察厅的总监
is also from Anhui.
也是安徽的
You all share the same hometown.
都是乡党
Why can't you just bend the rules for old folks.
你们怎么就不能通融一下
No wonder Tang Erhe said,
难怪那个汤尔和说
he just can't handle you people.
就是看不惯你们这些人
I think this Tang Erhe guy
我觉得这个叫糖耳朵的
isn't a good person.
不是什么好东西
Indeed.
就这个汤尔
He seems to pick on Zhongfu a lot recently.
最近好像一直在挑仲甫的刺
It's not him targeting Zhongfu.
不是他挑刺
It's Zhongfu who has gone too far recently.
是最近仲甫做得太过了
Brother Yimo, I don't like the sound of that.
尹默兄 你这话我就不爱听了
How come Zhongfu went too far?
仲甫哪儿做得过了
Haven't you read these days' newspapers?
这些天的报纸你没看哪
They're all coming at Zhongfu.
都是对着仲甫来的
All kinds of criticizing.
可是说什么的都有
Now even Mr. Cai is involved.
现在把蔡先生都卷进去了
Shen.
老沈
I think where you stand is not the right side.
我觉得你的立场很有问题啊
Who are you defending?
在帮谁说话
There is no problem where I stand.
真不是我立场有问题
I'm worried about Mr Cai.
我是为蔡先生担忧
I heard this morning.
听说今天一大早
Fu Zengxiang called Mr. Cai again
傅增湘又把蔡先生
and asked him to go to the Ministry of Education.
请到教育部去了
I guess it's about Zhongfu again.
估计又是仲甫的事
Brother Jiemin.
子民兄
You know where my heart favors.
你知道我的思想倾向
I support you and Chen Duxiu in developing a New Culture,
我是支持您和陈独秀搞新文化的
but now the pressure is too heavy.
可是现在压力太大了
We are all responsible for the fate of our country.
你我都担着国家的干系
No personal feelings should be mixed into this.
容不得掺入个人感情的
This is a joke, isn't it, brother Yuanshu?
你这是说笑话吧 叔兄
Is this a matter of personal feelings?
这是个人感情的事吗
This is about principle and justice.
这是原则 是公理
Isn't it?
是吧
Justice?
公理
Even justice has people's judgement in it.
公理是需要人来判定的
Now Zhang Changli is putting "New Youth",
张长礼拿着 《新青年》
"The Renaissance",
《新潮》
and "Citizen"
还有《国民》
on trial,
三本杂志到处告状
accusing you, Cai Yuanpei and Chen Duxiu
说你蔡元培和陈独秀
that you are sinners against the law and justice.
实为纲常名教之罪人
He also wants to impreach me as the Minister of Education
他要弹单劾我这个总长
and you, the President of Peking University.
和你这个北大校长
Yesterday,
昨天
Ma Jichang also took some copies of New Youth
马其昶也拿了几本 《新青年》
and made a scene at the presidential palace.
大闹总统府
He requested Xu Shichang to put cuffs on you and Chen Duxiu
要徐世昌对妖言惑众
and said you two are endangering the government.
危害朝纲的蔡元培和陈独秀
No mercy shall be spared.
严惩不贷
Look at these newspapers and magazines.
你再看看这些报刊杂志
It's all news about Peking University.
全是你北大的新闻哪
The chairman of the Confucius School in Anhui
这个安徽孔教会的会长
is Ma Jichang?
是马其昶吧
He came to Beijing,
他跑到北京来
here?
来了
Not alone.
不光他来了
He also brought several
他还带了好几个
remnants of the Tongcheng School.
桐城派的遗老遗少
Came all the way just to complain.
专门告状来了
I also want to tell you.
我还要告诉你
Police Chief Wu Bingxiang
警察总监吴炳湘
also sent me a watch list.
也给我发来了监控名单
There is your Peking University in it.
里边就有你北大的
Chen Duxiu and Li Dazhao.
陈独秀和李大钊
Brother Yuanshu, nothing you told me is new.
叔兄除了你告诉我的这些
As for those I dont know
我知道之外
and whatever, you didn't tell me.
就是你没告诉我的
It's also within my expectation.
我也是预料之中
I want to thank you though,
我要感谢你
for your care and support for Peking University.
对我们北大的关心和支持
Brother Jiemin.
子民兄
I want to remind you that you need to reconsider your approach.
我是要提醒您注意方式
Adapt and adjust.
善于通融
You know me well.
您知道
I, Cai Yuanpei, am not that kind of bull.
我蔡元培不是那种蛮牛之人
I'll be accommodating wherever I can.
能通融的地方我一定通融
I will see myself out.
好告辞了
It was nice seeing you.
告辞
Until next time.
慢走
Today's newspaper!
新出的报纸
Come get your newspaper!
要不要买报纸啊
Daoxiao noodles!
刀削面
Jiang,
老姜
go back to Peking University first.
你先回北大去吧
Just drop me off here.
你把车停在边上 我下来一下
You go back first.
你先回去吧
All right.
好
Jia!
驾
Selling newspapers! Selling newspapers!
卖报了 卖报
Today's newspaper!
刚出的报纸
Selling newspapers!
卖报了
New newspaper just came out!
刚出的新报纸
Come and see!
过来看看
Hello, sir.
先生 您好
Has today's newspaper come?
今天的报纸来了吗
Yep.
到了
What newspaper do you want?
请问您要什么报
I'll take the "Gazette".
我就要《公言报》
Okay.
好
Thank you.
谢谢
You're welcome.
不客气
Take care, sir.
先生 您慢走
Alright.
好
Selling newspapers! Selling newspapers!
卖报了 卖报
New newspaper just came out!
刚出的新报纸
Grab one!
卖报了
Take a look!
来 看一看
Today's newspaper!
刚出的新报纸
What can I get you, sir?
先生 吃点啥
Wonton, please.
来碗馄饨吧
Okay!
好
Gentlemen, I said to Cai Heqing
诸位 我对蔡鹤卿说
that the university is the leader of all educational insitutes.
大学为全国师表
It shall be the moral example for all else.
五常之所系属
Cai Heqing, you are the principal.
你蔡鹤卿身为校长
Your job should be to discipline teachers
理当管好教员不要胡闹
Instead what do you think you are doing?
而你们却叫器什么
Shouting loudly about get rid of the traditional examination system.
去科举废八股
This old man will never give in!
老夫绝不答应
Exactly.
是
I am getting close to my end.
老夫年垂七十
The first 30 years in my life, all the wealth and fame are like ashes now.
富贵功名前三十年视若弃灰
Old I might be, tough I will be.
今笃老尚抱守残缺
I'd rather die to see you get your way.
至死不易其操
What Master Qin said is right.
琴公所甚是
That is well-said, Master Qin.
琴公言之有理
Very well said!
说得太好了
Good point!
说得好
Enter.
各位
Please enter.
各位请
Please.
请
Gentlemen.
诸位
I also said to Cai Heqing.
我还告蔡鹤卿
In this world, only true academics with true morals
天下唯有真学术 真道德
can be ones urging others to follow.
始足独树一帜使人景从
Distinguished gentlemen.
各位高贤
In recent years, Chen Duxiu and Hu Shi of Peking University
近年来北大陈独秀 胡适之
with Qian Xuantong have repeatedly challenged me.
钱玄同等屡对我发难
Defaming me as a nutjob of Tongcheng School.
污我为桐城谬种选学妖孽
I never responded.
我一直没有回应
This open letter published today,
今天发表的这封公开信
together with the novel Jingsheng,
连同那篇小说《荆生》
is the reply I have for the so-called New Culture school
就算作是我对所谓的新文化
A formal response.
做出的正式答复
Good.
好
Master Lin.
林公
Don't you have another novel?
你不是还有一篇小说
"Yao Meng"?
《妖梦》吗
When will it be published?
何时发表啊
I have withdrawn that novel.
那篇小说我已经撤回了
Withdrawn?
撤回了
Fengzai.
丰载
Wasn't Fengzai here just now?
丰载刚才不还是在这里吗
Teacher!
恩师啊
Fengzhun went to work-study mutual aid society again.
丰载准是又去工读互助社
Trying to break them.
挖墙脚去了
Above is the investigation of Zhang Fengzai
以上就是我们工读互助社
from our work-study mutual aid society.
针对张丰载的调查情况
Yannian.
延年
What do you have in mind?
接下来你们有什么想法
We were thinking,
我们这么想的
to first of all, keep our heads low.
首先就是不动声色
We must expose this plot
一定要在下一周的国会辩论会上
in the congressional debate next week.
揭穿他们的阴谋
It'll be better if we could convince Yi Qunxian's father
当然最好能说服
that he can side with us.
易群先的爸爸反戈一击
Other than that,
再有就是
we can tail Zhang Fengzai.
我们想在暗中地跟踪张丰载
See if we can find evidence.
看看能不能找到
Evidence that he bought off those journalists
他收买那些记者的证据
and then make it public.
然后把这些证据公布于众
Qunxian
群先
Are you sure you can convince your father?
你有把握说服你爸吗
We can't do it alone.
光靠我们肯定是不行
Mr. Shouchang, do you know Mr. Zhang Shizhao?
守常先生 您认识章士钊先生吗
He used to be my dad's boss.
他以前是我爸的上司
If he is willing to come forward,
要是他肯出面的话
there may be a turnaround.
可能会有转机
No problem.
这个没问题
Mr. Xingyan happens to be in Beijing.
行严先生正好在北京
I can take you to him.
我可以带你们去找他
Good.
好
Have you found out any of the reporters?
你们探听到有哪些记者了吗
I glanced at the list.
那个名单我扫了一眼
There is an English journalist Edward
我记得有英国记者爱德华
and Japanese journalist Sato Tetjiro.
和日本记者佐滕铁次郎
Okay, let's start with these two.
好我们就从这两个人入手
Mr. Shouchang.
守常先生
Mr. Cai asked you to hurry to the principal's office.
祭先生让你赶紧到校长室去一趟
Said there was something important to discuss.
说有要事要商量
Take a seat.
你们坐一下啊
I'm sorry, Mr Cai.
对不起 蔡先生
I'm late.
我来晚了
Mr. Shouchang, please sit down.
守常先生 快请坐
Yes.
好
What's going on?
怎么了
Lin Shu asked Zhang Shizhao sent me a message the day before yesterday.
前天 林托章士钊给我带话
Said that he had already pull back
说是他已经把准备要发表的
his second novel.
第二篇小说给撤回去了
But yesterday,
可是昨天
he published an open letter to me.
他就发表了对我的公开信
Today,
今天
a novel came out.
就发表了这篇
A novel called "Yao Meng"
叫《妖梦》的小说
Yucai, you are a novelist.
豫才你是小说家
You shall be the one to have a better look at this
我请你这个周公啊
This "Yao Meng"
来解一解他这个 《妖梦》
"Yao Meng".
《妖梦》
"Yao Meng" is about
《妖梦》 讲的是
a man named Zheng Sikang
一个叫郑思康的人
sleepwalking to the underworld.
梦游到了阴曹地府
He saw a place
看见了一个
called a simple words school.
这么叫自话学堂的地方
The school is full of little devil-like beings.
学堂里全是一些魅
There is a pair of couplets in the hall.
堂前呢有一副楹联啊
The top line says: how incredible
上联道 白话通神
"Dream of the Red Chamber" and "Water Margin" is in the vernacular?
红楼梦水浒真不可思议
The bottom line says: traditional writings have lost their charm,
下联为 古文讨厌
who are Ou Yangxiu and Han Yu?
欧阳修韩愈是什么东西
There is also a hall called "End of Confucius" in the school.
学堂里还有一间毙孔堂
Also there is the couplet:
堂前也有一副楹联
animals are truely free, with no bounds from morality,
禽兽真自由 要这伦常何用
being noble is troublesome, all the better to discard it.
仁义太坏事 须从根本打消
Yuan Xu, the headmaster of the school,
学堂的校长元绪
is whom Zhu Xi mentioned in the "Analects" of Confucius
是朱熹在《论语集注》中
called Cai Dagui.
所提到的蔡大龟
This obviously refers to Mr. Cai.
这很明显 指的是蔡先生
Dean Tian Heng,
教务长田恒
Deputy Provost Qin Ershi,
副教务长秦二世
also allude to brother Zhongfu and Shizhi respectively.
也分别影射的是仲甫兄和适之
These creatures described in the novel
小说描写的这些妖人呢
take a strong stand on bring the end to Confucious,
沉一气高挂毙孔堂
promoting simple words,
高唱自话诗
shouting about the abolition of ancient Chinese literature.
高论废除古文
What happened after is
结果
they angered Asura, king of the underworld.
把阴曹地府的阿修罗王就惹怒了
In a fit of anger,
一气之下
Asura ate them all
把这些人通通吃掉
and turned them into smelly feces.
化成了臭不可闻的粪便
Yucai, I didn't hear you clearly.
豫才 我没听清
Was it that they ate us
是他们是把我们吃掉
or they ate the smelly feces?
还是把那个什么臭不可闻的粪
Eat us up
把我们吃掉
then turn into smelly feces.
化成臭不可闻的粪便
I thought they had a feces feast.
我还以为直接吃呢
Zhongfu, don't make fun of it at this time.
仲甫这个时候就不要调侃了
It should be said that Lin Shu's novel is very repulsive.
应该说林经这篇小说是很恶劣的
But, I think what's worse
其实我觉得更恶劣的
is this article in the "Gazette" newspaper:
是《公言报》 上登的这篇
"The recent changes of Peking University's ideological trend".
《请看北京大学思潮变迁之近况》
This article is completely
这篇文完全是
full of the tone of a politician.
安福系政客的口吻
It says
文章里头说
that ever since Cai Yuanpei took charge of Peking University,
说蔡元培氏执掌北大以来
he has hired the wrong people,
所用非人
and the corruption of scholars' habits is obvious to all.
败坏士习 有目共睹
Professor Chen Duxiu of Peking University
北京大学教授陈独秀
regards himself as the leader of the new school.
以新派首领自居
Among the teachers,
教员中呢
it's not only Chen Duxiu that is complicit,
写陈独秀縫一气的
there is also Hu Shi, Li Dazhao, Qian Xuantong,
主要有胡适 李大钊 钱玄同
Liu Bannong, Gao Yihan, and more.
刘半农 高一涵等
Students follow blindly.
学生更是闻风而起
There is no shortage of exaggeration.
张大其辞者 亦不乏人
And the article also said
而且文章里头还说
the new trend of thought in Peking University
北大的新思潮
has caused public resentment.
已经引起了公惯
The Ministry of Education has ordered Peking University
教育部已经责令了北京大学
that Chen Duxiu, Hu Shi, and Qian Xuantong
要把陈独秀 胡适 钱玄同
are to be expelled.
这三个人开除
Ah, this.
这个啊
I was on my way here just now
我刚才在来的路上
and bought the "Shenzhou Daily" newspaper.
买的《神州日报》
The "Bangu Lu Xun" column said
里边的《半谷通讯》中说
Chen Duxiu, Hu Shi,
陈独秀 胡适
Tao Menghe, Liu Bannong, and others
陶孟和刘半农等人
are already subject to government involvement.
已经受到了政府的干涉
It said Chen Duxiu had a pessmistic attitude
还说陈独秀态度消极
and has left Peking University.
并且已经离开了北大
They are not letting this just settle down.
树欲静而风不止啊
I've already put up with it again and again.
我已经是退避三舍 一忍再忍
However, these people are pushing even harder.
然斯人却步步紧逼 不依不饶
Heavy clouds upon a city can be stressful.
黑云压城城欲摧
But the sun will always come out and tear the darkness apart.
申光向日金鳞升
Then let me, this so-called Cai Dagui,
那就让我这个所谓的祭大龟
go into battle and fight.
只好披坚执锐 上阵斯杀吧
Great, Master Cai.
好蔡公
Even though I'm a smelly shit,
虽然我是个臭不可闻的臭大粪
I won't bend.
但岂能摧眉折腰
This pen in my hand can sweep a thousand troops.
我必当和您一起笔扫千军
We will keep going.
一鼓而荡之
In his poem "The Song of the Stormy Petrel",
俄国作家高尔基
Russian writer Gorky wrote
在《海燕之歌》上
this one line
有这么一句话
"Let the tempest come strike harder!".
让暴风雨来得更猛烈些吧
Recently,
近来
Lin Shu, who claimed to be a Qing imperial scholar had a big talk.
自称是清室举人的林大发议论
Claiming
号称是要
to guard the code of education and ethics of the Republic of China.
维护中华民国的名教纲常
Of course, he can say whatever he wants.
当然 这本可由他自语
Nothing to do with me.
与我无涉
But look at his impetuous behaviour.
但是看他那个气闹哄哄的样子吧
I again feel pity.
我又觉得很可怜
I can't help but try to persuade him.
我就忍不住想劝他几句
I want to discuss with you all how I can persuade you.
想跟你们商量商量我怎么劝
Since you regard yourself an old scholar of the imperial Qing,
您老既然不是国的人
then you should not care about the matters of the Republic of China.
那就少管国的事吧
Worrying less is good for you.
少操闲心少淘闲气
After the war, we see how right triumphs over might.
近来公理战胜
Did you?
您老可好
A person who claims loyalty to the imperial Qing
一个清室之人
came to the Republic of China,
跑来民国
let a man named Zheng Sikang
让一个叫郑思康的人
to sleepwalk to the underworld,
梦游到阴曹地府
seeing creatures roaming in the simple word school
看见一群魅阙在白话学堂里
that's putting an end to Confucius,
高挂毙孔堂
advocating the vernacular,
高唱白话诗
promoting the abolition of classical Chinese.
高谈废除古文
As a result,
结果
he provoked King Asura and had them all eaten.
把阴曹地府的阿修罗王
After the anger,
惹怒了以后
not only that,
把他们通通吃掉
he even turned them into smelly feces.
化成了臭不可闻的粪便
So I thought,
所以我就觉着啊
that no one
任何人你都不能去试图
shall try to stop the wheel of history.
阻挡历史前进的车轮
You need to obstruct it!
你非要挡呢
Then what is
那结果只有一个
the only outcome?
什么呢
It shall run over your legs!
被碾着腿嘛
Hurrah! Hurrah!
好好好
I'm telling those stubborn ghosts from old times,
我正告那些顽固 鬼崇
people with outdated minds.
抱着腐败思想的人们
You should stick to your principles
你们应该守着你们的道理
and stand up openly
光明磊落地站出来
to discuss with us, the new school of thought, in an open and honest manner.
和我们这些新派的思想论 讨论
If you want to hide behind others,
如果你们想隐藏在别人的身后
counting on them to cover you,
抱着你们那位伟丈夫的大腿
and put it in violence towards
用残暴的势力
those who oppose you
欺压反对你们的人
so you can feel better
为你们出出气
or even write a nonsense novel
或者写一篇鬼话连篇的小说
to relax yourself
快快口
and make up a rumor and be relieved,
造一段谣言宽宽心
then it's an utterly boring move!
那么这是极其无聊之举动
You must know that in today's China,
须知当今之中
if the youth are truly awakened,
如果有真正觉醒之青年
then they are not afraid
那么是断不怕
of your devastation.
你们的伟丈夫的摧残的
You, who claimed to be the noble man,
你们这些伟丈夫
can also never destroy the spirit of these young people.
也断不能摧残这些青年们的精神
Even back then, the tyrannical Russia
当日暴虐之俄国
has killed countless aspiring young people
不知道用了多少残暴的心性
with extreme cruelty.
杀了多少有志的青年
Who would know, it is their blood
哪知道这些青年的鲜血
that eventually
反倒成为了
cultivates the flower of revolutionary freedom.
培养革命自由之花的土壤
Those black prison cells
那些暗沉沉的监狱
instead, became the place for aspiring young fighters to rest
也反倒成为了有志青年
after they won the great battle.
奔波劳碌之后的休息场所
The oppression of the tyrannical government,
暴虐政府的欺压
in turn, provided some interest,
反倒为了我们这次革命
for us revolutionaries.
提供了一些些许的趣味
This growing, everlasting river
像今日这样滔滚滚的长流
is utterly unstoppable!
一发而不可遏呀
Long live the New Culture Movement!
新文化运动万岁
Long live!
新文化运动方罗
Fellow citizens,
同胞们
we advocate a new culture
我们倡导新文化
to seek liberation in all aspects:
就是要谋求各个方面的解放
the liberation of the mind,
思想的解放
the liberation of politics,
政治的解放
the liberation of the economy, the liberation of men and women,
经济的解放 男女的解放
and the liberation of education.
还有教育的解放
All have to rise above from the hell beneath
都要从九重冤狱
and see the broad daylight.
求见青天
Our Chinese nation
我们中华民族
is born with the greatest ability.
原有最伟大的能力
The deeper the oppression,
就是压迫越深
the greater the resistance.
反抗就越大
the more a spring is pressed,
蓄之既久
the faster it bounces back
其发必速
I dare to say this:
我敢说一句话
one day,
他日
the reform of the Chinese nation
中华民族的改革
will be more completed than any other nation,
将会比任何民族
and more thoroughly.
都彻底
Our society
中华民族的社会
will have a brighter future
将比任何的民族
than all the others.
都光明
Fellow citizens,
同胞们
we shall work hard
我们要努力
and go forward all the way.
拼命地向前
Our golden world,
我们黄金的世界
our glorious world
我们光华灿烂的世界
is right in front of us!
就在眼前
Great
好好好
Long live the New Culture Movement!
新文化运动方
Zhang Fengzai, what on earth is going on?
张丰载 这到底是怎么回事
You promised me again and again that you would withdraw the manuscript.
你一再向我保证撤稿了
Why is it published now?
怎么现在又登出来了
Explain it to me.
你给我解释清楚
Sir,
先生
I did convey it to the newspaper.
我我确实向报社传达了
Your request to withdraw the manuscript
您要求撤稿的意见
and they agreed.
而他们也答应了
I don't know.
我我不知道
What went wrong?
是哪个环节出了问题
Zhang Fengzai, you are no longer my student.
张丰载 你不是我的学生
You put me in this difficult situation
你陷我于不仁不义之地
and hade me an ungrateful oathbreaker.
你叫我如面对蔡卿
Now how can I face Mr. Cai, face the public?
如何面对大众啊
Sir, I have sent a letter to Cai Yuanpei
先生我已经致信蔡元培
to explain all this.
做出了解释
I will take all the responsibility.
所有的责任我来承担
Will Cai Yuanpei accept to your explanation?
祭元培会听你的解释吗
Can you even carry a responsibility this heavy?
这个责任你担当得起吗
You're a traitor.
你这个阳奉阴违
A shameless clown who deceives others.
欺上下 道貌岸然的小人
Teacher, let's calm down.
恩师莫急 恩师莫急
I say it's not a bad thing to confront them openly.
依我看 撕破脸皮也好啊
Anyway, next week,
反正我们下个星期
we will face Cai Yuanpei
就要和蔡元培
in court in front of Congress.
在国会上公堂对质了
Teacher.
恩师
Changli.
长礼
I am a scholar, you are a politician.
文人和政客
We are not on the same path.
道不同不相为谋
Now leave.
你们走吧
I never want to see you again.
我永远也不想再见到你们了
But teacher!
恩师
Leave now. I'm tired.
走吧 我累了
I will leave now.
学生告退了
Selling newspapers!
卖报了
Selling newspapers! Selling newspapers!
卖报了 卖报了
Read the new editions of "New Youth"
看新出版的 《新青年》
the "Weekly Review" and "The Renaissance"!
《每周评论》《新潮》
Peking University launched a big counterattack.
北京大学发起大反攻
New editions of "New Youth"
新出版的 《新青年》
and the "Weekly Review"!
《每周评论》
Come and read the newspapers!
来看报
Cai Yuanpei responded to Lin Qinnan.
蔡元培复信林琴南
Rewned discussion on the proposition of New Culture!
再谈新文化主张
See how Chen Duxiu face the rumors about Peking University!
看陈独秀直面北大谣言
Li Dazhao on the fierce battle between the old and new thoughts!
李大钊纵论新旧思潮之激战
Lu Xun sent another message to warn the traditionalists!
鲁迅再发文敬告遗老
Selling newspapers!
卖报
Selling newspapers! Selling newspapers!
卖报 卖报
I'm sold out.
哥我都卖完了
Selling newspapers!
卖报了
Now Comrade Yu Xiusong, please.
下面请俞秀松同志
Tell everyone about their tasks tonight.
给大家讲一下今晚的任务分工
Alright.
好
Let me explain it first.
我先说明一下
This action is forbidden to record.
本次行动禁止记录
Now hear me out.
现在我宣布一下
This is what we will do tonight.
今晚的行动分工
The first group:
第一组
He Mengxiong and Shi Cuntong,
何孟雄 施存统
you two are responsible for escorting Yi Qunxian
你们一人负责护送易群先
to meet Congressman Yi Kuilong.
去见国会议员易蔓龙
You are to convince Yi Kuilong
任务是说服易夔龙
so he will cancel the joint proposal with Zhang Changli
取消与张长礼联合提议的
and pull off the impeachment of Education Minister Fu Zengxiang
弹劾教育总长傅增
and Peking University President Cai Yuanpei.
北大校长蔡元培的议案
Also, he will not talk in the court.
并不到会做提案说明
But what if my dad doesn't want to see us?
可是我爸不愿见我们怎么办
Mr. Li Dazhao said
李大钊先生说
Mr. Zhang Shizhao
章士钊先生
already called your father.
已经给你爸爸打过电话了
He will meet you all
他同意见你们
in addition to handing over
你们除了要转交
Mr. Zhang Shizhao's letter.
章士钊先生的信件之外
More important
更重要的是
is convincing Yi Kuilong
要说服易蔓龙议员
to work with us.
配合我们的行动
Whether your task is a success or not
你们的任务能不能完成
is the key to our whole mission that day.
是那天我们整个任务行动的关键
Clear.
明白
The second group:
明自
Chen Yannian and Liu Mei,
陈延年 柳眉
you go find that journalist
你们负责去找
Edward, from the "The Times",
《泰晤士报》 记者爱德华
to expose Zhang Fengzai's plot
向他揭露张丰载的丑行
and win his support.
并争取他对我们的支持
Clear.
明白
The third group:
第三组
comrades of the screening group,
是我们放映组同志
you go find Japanese journalist Sato Tetsujiro,
负责去找日本记者佐藤铁次郎
same task as the second group.
任务与第二组相同
Clear.
明自
The fourth group:
第四组
Guo Xingang and Liu Haiwei,
郭心刚 刘海威
you are both students of Peking University.
你们是北大的学生
It's better you stay away from the public's eye,
不宜公开露面
so you two and Bai Lan will collect and sort out related information
带着白兰负责收集 整理
to print out
并油印相关证据材料
that we can use later.
以备当天使用
Clear.
明白
Task assignment is complete.
行动分配完毕
Everyone feeling confident?
有没有信心
Yes!
有
Let's go!
行动
Understood!
是
Uncle, I don't know what happened these two days.
二叔这两天也不知道怎么了
I have this bad feeling.
我总有一种不好的预感
What's going on?
怎么了
You sent that letter to Cai Yuanpei?
你给蔡元培的信送去了
It's been several days.
好几天了
Nothing happened since.
一点动静都没有
What does the letter say?
信上怎么说呀
I said I was a student in Peking University
我告诉他 我是北京大学的学生
and also a reporter working with several different papers.
身兼看好儿家报社的记者
Lin Shu was my teacher in Wuchang Middle School.
林是我在五常中学
He taught me.
读书时的老师
I refered his two novels
他的两篇小说
to the "New Morning Post"
都是由我分别推荐给 《新申报》
and the "Shenzhou Daily".
和《神州日报》的
Lin Shu did ask me to
林确实曾经要我
withdraw "Yao Meng".
把《妖梦》 给撤回来
But by that time they have already printed it.
但是由于报社已经发排
It didn't go as he wanted.
未能如愿
This responsibility should be borne by me.
这个责任应该由我来承担
But I think,
不过我认为
Lin Shu's two novels
林的这两篇小说
are truly of the best of literature.
堪称文学极品
Peking University should have a bigger heart
北大应该有这个胸怀
and publish them in school.
将它们在校发表
Silly boy.
傻小子
Didn't you add fuel to Cai Yuanpei's fire?
你这不是给蔡元培火上浇油吗
Now he won't spare you.
他能饶得了你呀
That's exactly what I want.
我就是要让他发火
The moment he's onto me, all his so-called free thoughts
他一发火 他的那套思想自由
and compatibility will be blown away.
兼容并包的幌子就会不攻自破
You are a moth to a flame.
你这是飞蛾扑火呀
Ok, you have guts.
行 有种
By the way,
对了
I called Wu Bingxiang.
我给吴炳湘打了电话
As soon as you graduate from university
你大学一毕业
go to the metropolitan police department to take office.
就到京师警察厅去上任
You can pick any title you want.
什么你自己挑
I won't dissapoint you
总不能委屈了你这个
as a university law student.
学法律的大学生
Uncle, actually, I do want to stay in Peking University.
二叔 其实我还是想留在北大
They always say,
他们老是说
in the past, Peking University had a lot of money and people were stupid.
以前的北大钱多 人傻
It's easy to make a living and win some fame.
名声大 好混事
Did you learn nothing all these years?
明明德你是怎么明的
Nothing at all?
修齐治平你是怎么修的
Your mind is full of gunk.
满脑子糊涂强
You are exactly the kind that Chen Duxiu and Lu Xun talks about.
你就是陈独秀鲁迅说的那种
A sanctimonious person.
假道学
Rogue under a mask of scholar,
流氓身上披着个文人的外衣
and does bad things in the name of academic justice.
打着做学问的招牌净做坏事
This is you right here.
说的就是你
Well, I learnt it all from you.
不都是你教的吗
You should know yourself better.
你自己照照
I'll do it.
我来 我来
Need me to move a heavy pot after all.
搬盆花还不得我来
Uncle, stop talking about me.
二叔别老说我了
How's it going for you to go to Congress the day after tomorrow?
您后天去国会论的事怎么样了
The proposal was handed in early.
提案早交上去了
Yi Kuilong will take the lead.
易龙领衔
He will explain the proposal the day after tomorrow.
后天 由他做提案说明
So I can hide behind the scenes and watch.
这样我就躲在幕后当旁观
I see, stay out of the mess.
看热闹啦
Do you think their proposal can be passed?
您觉得他们这个提案能通过吗
No way.
想都别想
To pass a motion,
通过提案
two thirds of the votes are required.
需要三分之二的票数
Most members of Congress
国会大多数的议员
agree or sympathize with the New Culture Movement.
都赞同或同情新文化
There are many friends of Cai Yuanpei too
还有许多蔡元培的故旧新朋
It's impossible they will pass the proposal.
怎么可能通过提案呢
We planned all this.
我们弄的这个闹剧呀
It's only a show to disgust
就是想恶心一下
Cai Yuanpei and Chen Duxiu.
蔡元培和陈独秀这帮人
Shaking public opinion a bit is the bonus
造造舆论
along with putting more pressure on the government.
再给政府施加点压力
That's all.
这样就行了
By the way, the most important thing is journalists.
对了 最主要是记者
The congressmen plus the audience that day
后天 到会的议员
won't make a big number.
还有旁听的人不是太多
Without the posture of a large number of journalists,
如果没有大批记者的架势
this show will fail
我们这个闹剧就成不了
Rest assured.
您放心
I've arranged everything.
我都安排好了
Nothing that money can't resolve
无非就是多花点钱呗
Is the manuscript ready?
稿子准备好了吗
You can trust me.
我办事 您放心
Be cautious.
谨慎再谨慎
Caution is the parent of safety.
小心驶得方年船
Understood.
侄儿明白